Share the screen.
0.
O.
Let me.
So today and tomorrow will be.
Anyways, because we will browse.
Avevi complex?
Sul code base.
And so it will at the same time.
These two classes will have different
purposes and goal and probably in many
ways very important to the main goal of
this course, so the run time.
We said that is the number of services
that are available during the execution
of a program that typically can be
compiled by the compiler. OK,
so we said that the runtime support,
the programming language as.
May vary.
In the case of the interpreted languages
is basically everything.
In the case even of C,
there is a the standard C library,
which is minimal but not empty.
Runtime support to support the language
and in the standard library you have
functions such as files,
such as memory allocation,
dynamic memory allocation.
Malloch and free are defined in the
standard C run time and printf we said
that it's even an interpreter because it
has a little bit of interpretation in
there, so.
No matter whether the language is system
oriented and highly compiled or.
Close to an interpreter,
there is some runtime support.
During the 90s,
this is a very brief recap just to set
things in the right perspective.
Everybody was re-implementing over and
over in C plus plus the same code,
so reference counting.
Now I can mention it without having to
explain it. Caper's collection.
Multithreading UI Graphics.
And so at some point,
the industrial world started to say.
Maybe we have to make the runtime support
grow.
Because in the modern programming,
having only the printf and few other
things, it's too little.
In order to support modern programming,
OK,
and that was basically one of the main
reasons for Java.
Probably even more for dotnet,
dotnet started in 96 as a secret project,
mostly because Microsoft tried to use
Java,
but some microsystem that was the company
developing Java made a legal action.
Ora.
Implementation issues and so Microsoft
started a secret project that was dotnet
in 96 and it took them a team of 600
people working for five years in order to
deliver.
this runtime.
Java in dotnet are the last.
Pig Execution Environment.
I mean,
there are no other attempts to provide in
such a structured way a comprehensive set
of feature for a programming language.
And in case of the net,
there was the additional goal to be a
general.
Runtime support,
so usually the runtime of C,
so you got the compiler and the C runtime,
you have rust and the C rust runtime
etcetera.
So typically there is some sort of
coupling between.
The language and the runtime Java was
mostly started like that,
so basically it was Java,
Java compiler and Java virtual machine
designed only to run Java compile code,
even though.
Later,
other programming languages have been
developed to target the Java byte code
that wasn't part of the original design
of the system and on the other hand.
Dotnet came up with the idea of creating
a general purpose multi-language runtime
OK, so there was it was declared.
That the dotnet runtime should have been
a universal runtime for all the
programming languages,
because all programming languages require
garbage collection, just in time,
type system, dynamic type checking,
etcetera.
OK, and so they said, OK,
let's design a universal runtime. In fact,
the first name,
the intername was one of many was URT
universal runtime. OK,
in fact dotnet was decided something like
few weeks before.
The public announcement before there were
a plethora of internal names in the
project that have changed over the years
and to validate this strong idea.
That the runtime was able to to be
targeted by different programming
real-world programming languages,
Microsoft started a secret project.
Around 99 there was called project seven,
so might have implemented seven
programming languages for targeting the
runtime and academia would have
implemented.
Other.
Sorry.
Yeah, so to the audience, I'm sorry,
I didn't notice that I had a muted mic,
so long story short, the run time.
Java,
virtual machine and dotnet are pretty
unique and they eventually represented
the attempt to create a universal runtime
for targeting multiple languages,
very short resume.
What I said so far, sorry,
so that is the universal runtime,
so it's interesting to browse a code base.
Of such a complexity on multiple levels
with respect to this course, OK, so.
During the last class,
I briefly introduced git and started
poking around in the in the code base,
now today I will try to introduce you.
Possibly with interaction with the class,
the core concepts,
and then we will learn a couple of ways
of browsing the code base,
one is by using your knowledge directly.
The other one is by using your knowledge
and asking question to the AI.
And you will see that it's interesting,
it's definitely interesting. In fact,
in GitHub now you have co-pilot to
interrupt with the code base because it's
clearly the way everybody's going to so.
Questo modo.
This is oops.
On time.
Sorry, OK.
Solisis ha.
The repo.
And the first interesting thing is that
this repo is a sort of history of
computer science,
in the sense that there are pieces of
code that have been developed starting
from the 90s.
OK, so you see different code styling,
the evolution of the way people the
pragmatics of program development and
also the names because there are.
Names such as, for instance,
EE execution environment,
which is something that if you see EE,
you won't think about execution
environment as a completion.
But the EE class is a crucial data
structure that makes the runtime work. OK,
so let's try to list.
The elements that you believe will be
useful in the in the implementation in a
runtime. OK, I mentioned a few keywords,
so I mean clearly we need a garbage.
Collector.
Why?
Because we learned that memory safety is
important and.
In the 90s, even the GCC compiler.
If you think, I mean,
GCC is the c compiler and c is a
programming language without automatic
memory management,
but the compiler started using a garbage
collector to work inside.
And that was mentioned as a proof that
now even the C compiler needed a garbage
collection,
so in the modern run time we need garbage
collection.
OK, so garbage collection,
then what do we need?
Memory manager, which is.
What are the functionality apart from the
garbage collection, which of course is?
No,
garbage collector for me is all but
you're right.
I mean memory management is not just the
garbage collection.
Garbage collector is part of the memory
management,
but this means stack manipulation.
If you remember.
The activation records are basically a
block of memory that is allocated on top
of the stack and contain local variables
for the thread executing,
so every thread has a stack.
Which is a segment into the memory of the
process,
and there is a stack pointer which tells
you where is the top of the stack,
and whenever you invoke a new function or
method,
you load a new activation record on top
of the stack.
So stack manipulation is an essential
activity and we will learn that that is
really, really important. By the way,
stack manipulation is also important
because if you remember garbage
collection, garbage collection.
Collection process works starting from
the roots and we commented that one of
the main sources for the roots.
Is the stack,
and so one of the things that the runtime
should be able is to walk and navigate
through the stack to find the roots and
to start the mark phase.
Of the garbage collection, okay.
Bene.
Runtime, this is the run time, so I mean,
we're trying to list essential,
so how do you think you can load the code?
You need a loader?
The loader is an essential component,
you have a binary file,
you want to load into the memory of the
process all the necessary information so
that you can execute the program.
Now,
one of the legacy of the contribution.
Second rosario, c'è una lezione,
ti posso vai shop.
I can so the loader is one of the
greatest contribution that Java made was
OK, we need type safe code because.
You're too young,
but when I was your age the PC kept
crashing for null point of the
referentiation,
so you're living in a world which is
basically type safe so you don't have.
The real experience of what does it mean
to have mostly C code that keep crashing
because the programmer don't follow
properly the conventions? OK so,
but in the 90s it was, I mean.
You kept rebooting your machine because
programs kept blowing up because of
dangling references and so back then it
was really, really important.
To have type programming because there
was an impact in the real world.
And Java, if you remember,
was originally introduced also for the
Internet of things,
so to program washing machine et cetera,
and a crushing washing machine is not a
good idea, so type safety.
Was really important and so the loader of
the runtime in the only two examples we
have of runtimes,
which are Java and dotnet.
Is the type loader.
So if you remember when we commented the
intermediate language, the byte code,
we said, OK, the byte code,
what it is is basically the definition of
types plus the byte code of the methods.
That is roughly a reasonable definition
of the content,
if you remember from the reflection OK,
and so the loader clearly is a key
element because is the component
responsible for laying out the memory.
And create all the elements so that the
runtime can start executing.
Notice that this you may think that this
is.
An easy notion, it's not.
Because Java when Java started,
Java started as an interpreter.
Because washing machines et cetera,
no EV code to execute et cetera.
But now when no,
back then when even Java introduced an
optimization called.
Just in time compiler.
So basically I compile on the fly the
byte code so that you execute execute
machine language for every method,
so the overhead you pay it it's neglected
and so you have a code which is.
Almost as fast as sì.
The last time I checked Java was still
One point six.
X with respect to C,
which still is the most fast programming
language you can have,
but you have to write a lot of code,
so I mean, the runtime can basically.
Come close to the performance of the C
language 1.6 if you wonder Python is 67 X.
OK,
that's if you were interested from where
this number comes,
if you look for Linux shutout,
there is an initiative to have multiple
benchmarks and programming languages and
have.
Yeah,
and they test different algorithms and
the average is this score. OK,
it's clearly roughly,
you can clearly find.
Bad situations in which this statement is
not entirely true,
but it's on the average true and in fact
we use Java quite a lot and dotnet mostly
on the Microsoft side because originally
it was Microsoft only technology and so.
It was bound to Windows and since 2016
has become open source and it's fully
multiplatform,
so now it's on part with Java OK,
so the loader is very important because.
One of the the important elements that
was introduced by Java and dotnet
preserved is the ability to load types at
runtime.
So you can extend literally.
A program while it's executing.
If you think of mission critical code,
this is really important.
Think of a driver model, driver model,
the driver model pattern is basically I
have an adapter that say, OK,
this is the interface of my device,
you implement the interface and through
the interface I'm able to.
Use your device OK,
we all use it to that basically thanks to
dynamic loading you can device a folder
in your system where you can put a binary
file.
That implements the interface that you
know,
so at compile time I know the interface
and through the loader I can dynamically
load this new executable that wasn't even
present at compile time.
OK, so in this way dynamic loading,
so loader is important for the.
Loading type, loading, etc. OK,
and of course is responsible also for
reading the binary format,
because the loader is the component which
is responsible for reading the binary
format.
and loads information to the memory.
Other components, we mentioned git.
Just in time.
Allora la mensa?
Exception ending.
And is also monitoring.
And performance.
And the bug.
This kind of series, I mean,
system have the bad habit of crashing and
then you must be able to understand.
What's going on? So the bug is important.
When I was working at the dotnet runtime,
there was Dario Russo, who was in Italian,
that was responsible for the
implementation of the reflection.
And actually it was able to debug by,
it was looked like matrix,
it was able to read the output of the JIT
in an exadecimal display.
and do the debugging of memory,
just reading the bytes.
Someone has to be able to do that.
Otherwise,
we all suffer of that painful activity.
Hello.
Yeah.
Let's let's write it there. I mean,
most of the dynamic memory management is
performed through garbage collection,
but it's not the only option.
There are inside the runtime dynamic
allocation.
The most use is to allocate the heap
segment that are garbage collected,
but it's not the only there is still one,
I mean.
OS functions OK,
quindi so io file network because Modern
time require network Java became popular
because.
They implemented the socket abstraction
in an acceptable way.
If you don't have suffered to see sockets,
you don't really get how revolutionary
was Java.
Java made the web connection so easy.
Ma you can create a web server in few
lines of code.
So that was revolutionary back then,
so network has become part of the runtime
with Java and of course with dotnute UI.
User interface,
because in the 90s command line wasn't
anymore the normal way of using computer,
so event driven programming became
popular thanks to Java.
And thanks to dotnet that moved on from
that point in dotnet,
they tried to create a.
User Interface.
They will host code can be compiled for
the native graphical user interface for
instance of Windows,
but also for the web interface.
And it was an ambitious project that
affected the architecture of web
application for four years,
and it's worth mentioning because the
ambition was okay conceptually the web.
Browser is a renderer similar to the
native UI renderer,
and so why should we write different
applications for the desktop or for the
web and many of the frameworks of today's?
Still are trying to go after this
incredible idea that back then was really,
really, but they failed to. I mean,
the problem also with Java, with the UI,
it was that UI.
Specially back then was where marketing.
Was happening? I mean,
cool interfaces were nice and so when you
start to use the subset that can be
implemented both on the web browser and
on the desktop,
you end up having a very limited set of
UI.
Functionalities,
and so eventually Microsoft,
when publicly announced,
came up with two libraries,
winforms and webforms.
Basically the type system was the same,
so the design.
Went through,
but basically they separated the project
because otherwise the risk was to make
unhappy both desktop programmers and web
programmers, OK?
The is still one important thing.
Oh yeah, or is function,
let's say threads.
Wecher.
Security,
I will mention security is a it's
important Java and dotnet introduce it in
the runtime because of this dynamic
loading mechanism.
The we introduced the a word in which a
process contains code not written by the
same motor.
And so there is a risk that since you
have access to the memory,
you can corrupt or read illegally data
since you are in the in the same memory
space.
And so the so-called code access security
was introduced so that Java and dotnet
could have been used in.
Banking on financial systems, OK.
That was another feature.
Another one.
The calling I would say the.
Interoperability.
Interoperability is a broad area which is
fundamental and at which Java wasn't that
good because Java was like we made the
perfect language,
everybody would write Java code and so
interoperability in Java was designed.
To be hard because everything should have
been Java, OK,
and that was one of the flows personally
I think of Java.
This idea that interrupt with other
languages should have been difficult
because everything was should have been
in Java,
but interoperability is essential because
you want to be able to use other
libraries and systems.
Written and developed in any other
language,
so the libraries follows a number.
If you remember,
there are a lot of conventions,
some of them imposed by the actual
architecture.
By the CPU.
OK.
Others imposed by the operating system,
so the PE,
portable executable is a standard which
tells you how to organize the physical
representation of an executable.
Okay,
because the executable inside must be
able to contain not only the code,
of course there is the code segment,
but for instance there is the text
portion where you can insert textual or
binary, I mean data not.
Program inside the binary,
and so all this there is a a a a formula
that is called cof,
which was standardized mostly by Unix,
Linux, et cetera,
and Microsoft did the PE,
which is a particular.
Distance of this format OK,
so there are a number of conventions that
you have to follow to be able to work,
and one of the convention that we
mentioned is how do we load the arguments
on top of the activation record?
OK,
because we said that the activation
record is the set of data which contains
the arguments that you're passing to a
function or a method from the
implementation standpoint and say it now
and that's it.
From an implementation standpoint,
a method is just a function with an extra
argument, which is the this point, OK.
So I will talk mostly.
Of functions and methods in a in a
interexchangeable way,
because at the end of the day are
callable objects and the static method is
basically a function and.
Instance method is simply a static method
plus one more argument,
which is this point. OK, so.
From now on,
we think like everything is a function
which simplifies our thinking.
So basically in the activation,
when you do the call,
you have first to load on top of the
arguments.
You need to have the return address.
There will be also some room for local
variables.
There are some other information that may
be required, for instance,
for implementing status scoping,
you may need.
To have some extra information on the
stack,
I'm not going to go in further details on
that,
but that's we will see that stack is an
interesting place.
All these conventions basically are
essentially.
Essential because those depends on the
programming language, on the compiler, OK,
I mean,
should we load from the first to the last
or from the last to the first?
As long as you read and write in the same
way, who cares?
But when you start trying to invoke
external libraries,
then this becomes of paramount importance
because.
The binaries have been obtained from
different programming language, possibly,
or even the same programming language,
but different compilers.
And so.
Sì, has become a de facto standard.
Because linux was developed in sì e in
Windows two.
Penso.
The DLS all the libraries inside the
operating system follows the calling
conventions of C.
No.
A variation of this,
so the calling convention remember that
the C programming language allows for the
print F and print F, not only print F,
print F is.
A good function to keep in mind,
printf allows for a variable number of
arguments, remember?
So this means that when you load the
arguments on top of the stack,
you the collee,
so you load the I am the caller,
I call the load the stack with the
arguments.
Then I call,
so in the CPU I issue a call instruction,
I call the destination function which
will receive on top of the stack all the
arguments.
And she start working,
then eventually you want to return from
that function.
And someone has to clear the stack
because the activation record is no
longer needed.
Now.
Who is responsible to clear the stack?
The colis o the coler.
That's the point, I mean.
From a language programming perspective,
who cares is the right answer to the
question,
because as long as someone loves,
someone removes, I don't really care,
but from interoperability,
if you decide to have variable arguments.
Then you have this problem,
only the caller will be able to unload.
Che.
And this means that ad every function
call you will pay.
The stack clearance in the I mean,
those instruction will be executed anyway,
okay,
so from a performance standpoint there is
no difference because I have to unload
the stack and so.
Whether is the collee in making those
operations or the caller,
the amount of instructions executed will
be the same. So I mean,
there's no performance issues there,
but there is a problem,
the size of the executable file.
Will become bigger for C because every
function call you have in the call will
have the instructions to unload the stack,
so the C declaration calling convention
typically is not.
So appreciated,
special it was not appreciated in the 90s.
When the hard drive was 20 megabytes,
and so those few bytes for every call
were expensive on a PC.
And so the alternative was the Pascal.
Pascal now is basically dead,
but back then it was popular,
remember the P code, and so the.
In the,
because Pascal didn't have variable
arguments as a programming language,
the collee convention assumed that it was
the collee to unload the stack before
returning.
And that is non.
As a standard deckl and has become a
reference for operating system so that
you reduce the footprint of the
executable of the operating system, OK.
So that that's basically so
interoperability is.
I just discussed.
Loading the activation record e unloading
the activation record.
OK, suppose.
You have.
A point class,
let me write like this x and y.
How would you pass this data structure in
the variable on top of the stack?
Again, it's a convention,
I may pass y first and x after or vice
versa.
I can use a different alignment of bits
from for the number for the number
representation, the alignment.
Eccetera OK, so.
There is a huge problem of marshaling.
And I'm marshalling.
Data structures,
marshaling is the activity to load the
donkey back OK and unloading OK,
you have to basically take your objects,
load them.
In a way which can be supported by the
donkey and then unload it and restore the
order of things. OK,
that's the origin of the name.
And so the marshalling is basically
happens when a binary.
Representation of an object which is in
memory.
Should be transformed so that someone
else can receive it,
then this someone else may generate
another structured value that I have to
decode in order to be able.
To obtain the return value which is
structured in my internal presentation.
OK,
so all these things inside happen also at
the programming language level at the run
time, but the point is that.
Interoperability becomes of a paramount
importance because the language spoken by
your program is different typically than
the language spoken by another library,
which.
By the way,
can be a binary library at DLL.
But can also be.
A web service, a rest API, a soap message,
and so the marshaling and marshaling
activities are of crucial importance
because.
You need to be able to pass structured
information to other services and read
structured information as a result,
so JSON has become popular as a way of
marshaling and marshaling objects.
XML has been used used using XML schema
definition,
XSD has been used to implement the soap
standard for making the same through the
network.
OK,
and that has become one of the most
important things whenever you use some
remote services by adding a library to
your your system and then you call a
method,
basically what's happening behind the
code in is.
Someone prepares, marshal the data,
creates the sockets,
pass whatever it should be passed,
waits for the results,
parses the result and then returns the
structured value so that you don't have
to bother.
About this thing, and in fact,
the first example of this concept was
called RPC, remote procedure call.
But at the end of the day,
whether it's a web service, an HTTP API,
a rest API,
or an RPC or binary interoperability,
the sequence is always the same,
you invoke a function which is local to
your.
Program, this function takes the data,
performs the marshaling,
ensures that the data are in the correct
format as expected by the collee,
invokes the collee whether it is by
invoking.
Another process,
opening a socket to a remote place,
all the same,
wait for the result as long as you get
the result,
parse back the result and return the
structural result to the caller.
OK,
that's the the general pattern for
interoperability dotnet was really
interesting because they created the
runtime.
In a way which was designed to
interoperate with all the system,
so it is very easy to use external
libraries in dot net by using custom
attributes, remember custom attributes.
Now we will see one of the successful
applications,
so if the if a if a dynamic link linking
library a dll as a function let's say foo
declared then.
I can or let's say add,
so if I know that a function.
As di signature Inside DLL.
I can say DLL import.
Mai.
My DLL do DLL.
E automatically the run time.
Here I would say typically external
external something and then the run time
automatically will will perform the
invocation.
Of the add function inside the that
particular DLL,
so all the complex work that has to be
done to marshal the arguments and marshal
the results.
Will be performed by the runtime thanks
to that annotation. OK,
so interoperability is important. OK,
so now we have a.
Rather exhaustive list of all the
services that a modern runtime should
provide.
Really what made complicated.
In Java, in dotnet.
It was basically the just in time
compiler and the ambition to have a
standard by code.
OK, this makes things more complicated.
Now.
Ciao.
How do you think the execution should
happen?
I mean,
should should it work like an interpreter?
Or.
In a different way.
I have a Java code,
I have a dotnet code compiled,
I have the binary,
I say okay JVM run this Java name of the
assembly of the class or dotnet and run
and the assembly.
And then WhatsApp?
So the execution.
Can basically follow two approaches one
is.
Orchestrated by the execution environment.
That was basically the Java approach. OK,
so if you want to.
Be able to interpret things typically you
need that the virtual machine is the
orchestrator OK,
so basically the virtual machine loads
the class.
Then creates all the data structure,
then starts the execution of method upon
the return. Should I do something? OK,
I transfer the control to someone else.
OK, so the orchestration of the.
Program execution is mostly done by the
execution environment and you can try to
figure out in your mind like an
interpreter.
So there is a main loop which says, OK,
what's the next step?
Then you invoke the next step,
you wait for the result.
And then you decide the next action, okay?
The other way, the other.
Approach is a passive callback approach.
What do I mean for by this?
You,
if you in the in the in the in the
virtual machine,
all the code that is executed is is
generated by the virtual machine itself.
OK.
So if I have a C Sharp method that would
will be in byte code and run time will
generate the actual assembly and machine
language code on the fly for me.
OK,
so that's so something that I can do is
to generate the executable and do exactly
what the C compiler does,
the C compiler when compiles the program
generates.
Callbacks to the run time,
which provide the service.
So something that I can do is to.
Leverage on this core idea and create a
passive system which simply loads,
and for this reason the loader is very
important,
you lay out all the memory and then you
generate stubs all over the places.
That ensures that you will be called back
when a service from the runtime is needed.
Example,
One of the first implementation of the
dotnet runtime,
when the just in time was compiling a
jump backward.
OK,
so because you have the jump instruction,
the jump instruction scope is so you can
jump only inside the method,
so you can jump everywhere,
but nevertheless you have the jump and
this is.
How the while or for loop is implemented,
so whenever you have a jump instruction
which jumps to a previous instruction,
typically that's the sign of a loop.
The just in time compiler emitted a check,
should I run the garbage collection OK?
So in the program as the loop,
but the just in time annotated the
executable code so that you ensure that
the garbage collector will be invoked.
Otherwise,
the risk is that nobody calls the garbage
collector and the system will remain
without memory. OK,
so if you decide to go for a word in
which the code execute naturally in into
the memory.
You have to ensure that some services of
the runtime gets called at the proper
time,
then you can inject callback to the
internal libraries and this is the dot
net approach and personally I love it.
ah but that's my feeling.
Me so molto difficult to understand the
code, so.
But in general it's more efficient. OK,
so those are basically the all the
elements. OK, now you know about types,
you know about syntax, compilation,
runtime.
Scope, et cetera,
so you have all the ingredients to try to
understand how these things gets in fact
implemented in a real use case.
So.
This is the runtime.
First thing I'm going to do is let's do
as I would have done,
as I did 20 years ago. I mean,
I was able to download dot net source
code on my machine.
I waited something like half an hour to
get the full source code base of my PC
and then I started looking around trying
to understanding something so complicated
without any clue how to start. You start,
they were of course read me.
How to build and this kind of things,
but things were really complicated and I
started wondering, wondering myself,
how do I contribute to this thing?
Since it's so complicated to understand,
OK,
so you start browsing and clearly source
is the typical place where you go.
You have to figure out names and then you
have also to enter because sometimes
names are not so intuitive,
for instance if I want to have a look at
the object class.
Which was actually the first class I
accessed when I had access to the run
time,
because it's pervasive in the type system,
but you never see the implementation,
so I was curious to see how it was
implemented.
You have to look.
In rather counterintuitive place,
which is system private core lib,
because actually that is where you find.
The implementation.
I see.
The object core.
And I see some C sharp and I say, come on,
how is that possible? I mean,
this is the runtime.
How can I write things in C sharp in the
runtime? OK.
First of all,
I notice that there is a partial,
so this is not the full definition of the
class,
and this is a unique trait to dotnet,
which is a very geeky thing for
programming lovers.
Basically, Microsoft said OK,
is expensive to maintain a C plus plus
code base,
so let's define a mechanism in which I
can define a class,
for instance the object class partly in C
plus plus.
E partly in dotnet. OK,
because at the end of the day the layout
of the memory of the object is the same,
and so that should be doable. OK,
so I found the part of the object class
definition.
But is only the part which is not the
core part,
it's the one that allows you to have the
get type implementation.
And the unsafe keyword which is available
in C Sharp allows you to have a block
which is which contains pointer
management which is available.
This intrinsic.
Annotation relates its limited to the
runtime,
and basically it's a notation that helps
the runtime to generate the proper call
to the internal functions.
Because, of course,
the calling convention internally is
different than the calling convention.
Among methods.
Ok.
Let's try again.
Where do you look for?
In C++ it is part of the runtime there is
chicken and egg problem.
You're creating through the abstraction
all the types that are needed to obtain C
Sharp up and running. Okay, so.
You need to have a core set of objects
defined in C++ and not in C sharp itself,
otherwise it wouldn't bootstrap OK so.
You may look inside,
I will go and look inside the VM,
hopefully.
Object is so core,
it will be part of the VM,
maybe I'm lucky, I'm looking around.
I see names that are encourage me,
such as class, maybe there is also object.
EE, as you can see,
there are a number of EE files,
those are interesting.
Object looks like that.
Maybe.
OK,
object model CLR object is is a common
base part to all CLR objects. Yes,
we found.
So now you see that comments are properly
made in general when you write programs.
If you have for each a in array the line
of code on top,
I go over the elements of the array,
why are you inserting that?
It's clearly a stupid comment,
OK comment sul limit to.
Illustrate non obvious things such as
this one or to implementation choices
that may have been different.
So it's a good thing to remember why you
picked up that, OK?
There are some notes.
There are a number of forward
declarations in C++,
there is this notion of forward
declaration. So you say, okay,
there is a class method table,
don't worry,
I tell you it's there so that you can,
I can use it, okay?
Anna Anna.
At last.
We find that basically the object has no
fields.
Tecnically not is not a tightly true,
but almost.
And it has only a protected member,
which is.
Method table.
So when you studied the type system and
the inheritance,
you know that the essence of inheritance
polymorphism is the is a relation,
so if I have.
A superclass and a class that inherits
from that superclass an instance,
whenever is expected an instance of an
object of the superclass,
I must be allowed to indicate the an
object of the inherit class.
OK, that's by definition.
Niente.
This means that because you can override
the implementation of the methods.
That you can statically know which method
should be invoked in C plus plus.
There was a big,
huge debate during the 90s because.
In C plus plus,
the programming may decide whether AAA
method is virtual or not by virtual means
this method can be overridden by a
derived class if.
If it's not virtual,
then I don't care statically,
I must be able to know which version
should I invoke.
And if you need a virtual method,
you need some form of runtime type
checking, because only a runtime.
When you call,
you will have the reference to the object
and you will know the type so that you
can invoke the right version of some
method. OK,
and so the method table has become a
crucial data structure of any.
Runtime also the C Plus Plus runtime
because you need a table in which you
have all the pointers to the method
implementations or da particular class
thanks to this.
You can implement the override.
And you can make.
Different object coming from different
classes to point to different methods,
even to support the overriding of the
method. OK, so this is the method.
Table is a crucial element and Java said,
you know what, all the methods are vital,
that's it.
Why? Because by the end of the 90s,
it was basically impossible to tell the
overhead of having an indirection in the
call, because clearly,
if I have a method table with all the
pointers to the code for every.
Method, when I want to call the method,
I have to go to the method table and then
jump to the address.
And so clearly there is some little bit
little of red already by the end of the
90s,
it was impossible to tell the difference.
Between a code not using virtual methods
and a code using virtual methods so Java
set you know what?
O Vito.
Ma ci si dico,
scrivi if you allow to to decide.
Being sketch much more complicated so in
modern run times you whenever you have a
type,
you in fact have the pointer to the
method table and you have a method table
for every.
Class.
So whenever I load the class into the
memory,
I have only one method table that is
shared across all the objects instances
of that particular class,
which means that this point.
Tell me the class of the object.
Good so at run time you can always say
what is the class to which a particular
object belongs to,
and the answer is look at the at the.
Metho table.
Because there is one method table per
type.
OK, so this is a browsing style,
it's complicated because if you want to
learn how to work the git.
Things gets much more complicated.
OK,
because you will see a bunch of concepts
that even if you are familiar with the
programming language abstraction,
you may fail to understand.
There are technicalities optimizations
that are not so easy to spot,
so the code browsing that you
instinctively tend to do in a large code
place will not work.
There's no easy way to go and read a
story.
And everything is clear and neat.
It's much more.
If you are browsing a website,
that's easy. You look at the web URL,
you look at the corresponding page,
you understand the routing mechanism of
the particular runtime and then.
You understand the code generation?
It's still easy,
but here here is not that easy because
there are so many elements that are
interacting one with each other that even
reading the code is complicated.
So let's look for instance.
One CPP file.
Su.
It is full of register code gen gen
initialized registered state and then you
start calling internal services and there
are thousands of names and unless you are.
An expert in this particular thing,
even looking at simple stuff such as how
the add instruction is compiled is
complicated, OK,
so browsing the code base.
So complicated.
It's not easy. So of course,
the first thing you must do is look for
documentation.
There should be some documentation,
in particular the documentation of the
CLR if you.
Go into the docs of the run time.
There is a beautiful design,
I will start with the design because
design is architectural,
so I can look around and trying to
understand the concepts.
Not the details and of course I'm
interested in the core CLR,
which is the and then I find that there
are.
Free folders, GT is easy.
Profiling, you may guess botr,
this is what it is bot because bot now
for us sounds like bot chatbot,
but technically it's an acronym and it's
is book of the runtime, OK?
So you find an entire book,
which I encourage you to read as an
exercise.
It is full of really interesting
information, it is generally readable and.
I will use part of it just to give you
some.
Information OK, so as you can see,
there is a frequently asked question,
an introduction to the runtime.
It's interesting when you go to the
introduction because you see that this
has been.
Britten in 2007.
Ok.
Which is basically 10 years after the
definition, clearly.
The documentation of the runtime
internally to Microsoft there was a lot
of documentation, but that was private.
When Microsoft started working on an open
source release of the framework,
then some documentation has been.
Redefined also because the open source
version of the.
net has been simplified in some aspects,
but those are very specific with respect
to the original implementation,
which was too Windows dependent.
In some functions,
so basically they redefine some notion so
that the porting was easier than it was
originally OK.
In the list we can see important things.
Garbage collection design first. OK,
garbage collection is important.
Garbage collection is important because
the performance of your system will
depend upon the efficiency.
Of the garbage collection.
Trading is important.
Rio jit is the name of jit.
Type system is important,
type loader is important,
method descriptor is important,
method descriptor is the descriptor of
the method of the method table.
Is one of the elements is where the code
lies in these systems.
Virtuous Tab,
we will discuss something around but not.
Stuck working.
Stuck working,
we will find it's a very important
activity because the stack is a place
full of information and a lot of services
inside the runtime is made.
By performing stack walking.
Private con leap and calling in into the
run time, this is important.
Because remember the object class in C
Sharp that was invoking C Plus Plus part
of code that should be documented because
it's tricky.
And then other important things,
the API is a convention about the layout
of binaries. OK, so I mean, it's not.
OK in the last 15 minutes or so.
I will start with the garbage collection.
Because basically we discuss it
abstractly the garbage collector,
now we have the opportunity to read and
test ourselves if the things that we
discussed during the general introduction
of garbage collection.
Helps us reading this documentation.
The two components that belong to GC are
the allocator and the collector.
Of course, I mean,
I didn't explicitly mention,
but it was implicit because you have to
function in the garbage collection.
On one hand, you need to allocate memory,
remember in the copy collector,
you're appending data, et cetera.
And then you have the collector, which is.
When the markers we, when the markers we,
for copy Collection eccetera happens to
free the memory actually OK so.
The design.
The allocator gets called by the
allocation helpers in the execution
engine with the following information,
the size requested,
the thread allocation context.
And flags that indicate things like
whether.
This is a finalizable object or not?
So what is a finalizable object?
Remember the destructor,
both Java and dotnet have a similar
notion, the object may override.
A method which is called finalize that
will be called just before the garbage
collections dispose the object OK to free
resources has never been really popular
because you can't predict when it will be
called. It depends on how much memory.
You have in your system,
and so it's never been really popular as
a as a as a function,
but it's it has its useful use cases and
the garbage protection must.
Know whether a particular object has a
finalizer or not,
because in that case it should do
something,
otherwise it will simply skip that OK,
so you have a bunch of flags that tells
you information relevant information.
About the object.
The GC does not have special treatment
for different kinds of object types.
It consults the EE to get the size of an
object. This is important.
Remember that precise collection requires
at run time that you are able to fully
know all the elements of an object,
in particular the references,
the pointers.
Because that is essential for the
marketing face of the garbage collection
process.
Based on size,
the GC divides objects into two
categories,
small objects smaller than eighty five
kilobytes.
Eighty five thousand bytes and large
objects greater than 85,000 bytes.
Why is that?
NY eighty five.
Why not seventy three forty two?
Empirically,
so they run billions of computations and
they found out that 85,000 is reasonable,
is the best compromise because of course,
if it's larger,
you will pay some more cost if it's
smaller.
Some others 85 empirically has become a
good, it's a constant,
maybe can be changed,
but basically that is the reason, right?
And why we like to classify.
Objects in large and small.
To prevent.
Fragmentation of the memory,
because so basically large objects,
first of all, tend to live longer.
I mean,
if you're spending in your programming
effort in allocating more than 85
kilobytes,
that object is relevant for you. I mean,
it's not just few variables,
it's likely to be an important object.
Whether it's an array of lots of things
or whatever it is, nevertheless,
it clearly has a meaning,
and so it is likely that it will last for
long time, not only.
What the copy collection does when you do
the collection, you allocate a new heap.
You copy the survive the object in the
new heap and so if I have an object with
85 K,
then the cost of the copy collection
would be significant.
And this will slow my process,
and so it makes sense to classify these
two classes because large objects,
for instance,
are located in a single generation.
We mark and sweep and without generations,
because the cost of managing and copying
between generations objects is not
neglectable if objects are too large.
OK,
so when the GC gives out memory to the
locator,
so in terms of allocation context, OK,
there are let me skip. I mean,
I encourage you to read it because there
are a lot of interesting things.
So the allocator is designed to achieve
the following,
triggering a garbage collection when
appropriate.
Preserving object locality.
Because as I already anticipated when I
was talking about garbage collection,
garbage collection is typically not
implemented in a single heap,
typically you allocate heap in size of
let's say one megabyte.
RAM, which is reasonable,
and then you manage that heap through
garbage collection, OK, and so.
Having objects that reference objects in
different types may have some costs,
not in terms of performance because I
mean it's memory,
but for instance in terms of blocking
because the gamers collector.
To operate must suspend the execution of
one or more threads,
and so if you spread too much information
to the memory,
you may generate contention for the
concurrent execution.
Efficient cache usage, of course,
efficient locking, because one of the.
Criticism that are made that was made to
garbage collection is that garbage
collection, specialty copy collection,
requires you to stop the execution
because you're copying objects around,
which means that you can't execute.
Anything during this process,
because otherwise the risk is that some
code will touch some object that has been
moved,
but the reference has not yet been
updated. OK, and so.
When the garbage collection is triggered,
some part of your application will stop
and the naive implementation stops
everything,
then you collect and then you resume
everything, but clearly this is rather.
Expensive,
there are concurrent approaches that may
reduce this phenomenon.
Memory integrity,
the GC always zeroes out the memory.
For newly allocated objects, OK,
this is for security.
This ensures for instance there are there
is no spill of information by allocating
and allocating objects because the
garbage collection gives you back zero
memory all the time.
Keeping the hip crawlable.
So the allocator make sure to make a free
object out of left over memory in each
allocation quantum.
So basically if there are 30 bytes left
in an allocation quantum and the next
object is.
Forty bytes,
the allocator will make the 30 bytes a
free object and get a new allocation.
This is the what you do when you saturate
the hip, OK and.
Guess what you have unlock to allocate,
and this is the allocate easy and nat.
The collector,
clearly the collector is the most
interesting part.
So.
The GC is a generational collector.
Which means that objects are logically
divided into generations,
and we already studied this.
So you start with generation zero is
where allocation happens,
and then collector will move across
generation from generation n to
generation n plus one.
For small objects,
the heap is divided into three
generations.
This is an implementation choice.
Of course, you can imagine n generation,
but at the end of the day,
in this implementation,
you have three generations, gen zero,
gen one and gen two.
For large object,
there's one generation gen three.
This gives you also a int gentry is is
marquez VIP.
Che.
Gen zero and Gen One are referred as
ephemeral.
So.
Is where objects that are short-lived
tend to stay because time from different
collection makes are wider than the
lifespan of that particular object.
So.
The managed dip is a set of managed dip
segments, as I was telling,
so it's not a single pool of memory.
Here you find you find few information,
I'm just stopping on the relevant the
flow of a garbage collection,
there is a mark face the mark face.
Is important both in copy collection and
in mark and sweep because mark, we said,
is the way we prove that an object is
still reachable from the roots and
potentially accessible.
During the rest of the program execution.
There is, and this is interesting,
a plan phase,
the plan phase simulates a compaction to
determine the effective result if
compaction is product.
The GC starts an actual compaction,
otherwise it sweeps.
So technically the ephemeral generation
are hybrid, they're not copy collectors.
I tricked you, I was too simplified.
Because there are situations in which the
copy collection is not convenient.
And so the implementation say, OK,
let's simulate. I did the mark,
so I know what I should free.
Now let me do a simulation.
Is it convenient to do a copy a
compaction?
Through copy collection, yes or no,
it's not convenient, then I do this weep.
It is convenient,
then I do the compaction,
so if I do the sweep,
then clearly the allocator will allocate
blocks in that segment, not.
Appending as it is custom for the copy
collector.
Ib CC decide to compact.
Then reference must be updated.
It is a the compact phase is important
because you have to backpatch.
That's the titter backpatch backpatch
means that you go.
Back and you update the reference to the
object because you move the object and so
you have to update its reference.
And of course,
as you can see from the comment,
this space is very straightforward since
the plan phase already calculated the new
addresses the object should move to OK,
because you simulate,
so you already pre-compute the target and
so.
If you do it, you already have it,
so you have just to update the sweep face.
The Swift face looks for the dead space
in between live objects.
It creates free objects in place of these
dead spaces. OK,
so the one we already commented.
So you basically mark us free the blocks
so that the allocator later will find
these chunks and will allocate objects
again in that in that space, that's it,
okay?
Of course.
Decide whether to compact or not a
segment is relevant because if you.
Do only the sweeping.
The risk is that you fragmented so much
the heap that the empty spaces are too
small, and so if you aggregate together,
you will have not space to allocate the
new object, but since.
All the leftovers are small enough,
you have to allocate a new segment to
allocate a new wasting memory,
so it's all about trade off and when you
are implementing the runtime.
Of a language you are,
you are as close as the CPU as possible
and the costs are measured in single
instructions,
so strategies that you may have studied.
Interpreting systems,
which are doable when you're dealing with
processes,
there are big things are simply not
possible at the programming language
level.
OK.
Let's physical architecture.
Which is basically pseudo code that helps
you to understand the logic.
And then there are few comments about the
concurrent garbage collector.
There is one thing.
With which I finish that I didn't mention
during the garbage collection because
it's just an optimization,
but it's really important.
To keep in mind,
it applies for sure at dotnet,
but it's not the only place where it has
been used in dotnet made a huge
difference when we was introduced,
which is a technique known as right
barrier.
What is a right bad? It's a big mask.
So there are data structures that are
called cards into the memory,
which are just bits,
every bit maps infect to the a part of
the memory.
And the goal is to record all the
assignments to reference that is made by
your program,
so if your program has a store.
Location or store field,
which are the intermediate language
instructions to store a value into a
local variable or field,
which is a reference.
Then this will trigger a bit set in the
right barrier to indicate that that field
has changed value. OK, why is that?
Because.
This allows you to not have to browse all
the time, all the memory. Basically,
when the garbage collection starts,
you say, OK, let me look.
Which part of the memory has been changed?
I just collect that part because the rest
is as it was before in the previous run,
so it's already okay, right?
So the right barrier,
it's interesting because of.
Of course, the cost of assigning.
A reference,
it costs you more operation because it
costs you to set the reference plus set
the bit mask somewhere,
but at the same time this reduce the time
significantly.
Of the garbage collection execution,
which is much more relevant so and when
you write clearly you are spending more
computing cycle to do that,
but the when you do the assignment it's
threat safe.
So technically you can write without
affecting the concurrency,
whereas the garbage collection in any
case will affect the concurrency of a
program.
And so clearly in the equation and the
balance of the performance cost less to
pay a little bit more for a reassignment
to a reference rather than having to roll
all the keep all the time. OK,
so the right barrier is an interesting
technique which actually is in production.
I don't know.
If Java uses but for sure dotnet uses OK,
so tomorrow we will start and complete
this,
we will look into the type loader type
layout stack rolling and we will have
also an example of how to browse.
With AI a code base like this OK,
thank you.